<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://www.isa-afp.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Archive of Formal Proofs</title>
    <link>https://www.isa-afp.org</link>
    <description>
      The Archive of Formal Proofs is a collection of proof libraries, examples,
      and larger scientific developments, mechanically checked
      in the theorem prover Isabelle.
    </description>
    <pubDate>13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <item>
       <title>Formalization of Timely Dataflow's Progress Tracking Protocol</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Progress_Tracking.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Progress_Tracking.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Matthias Brun, Sára Decova, Andrea Lattuada, Dmitriy Traytel       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
Large-scale stream processing systems often follow the dataflow
paradigm, which enforces a program structure that exposes a high
degree of parallelism. The Timely Dataflow distributed system supports
expressive cyclic dataflows for which it offers low-latency data- and
pipeline-parallel stream processing. To achieve high expressiveness
and performance, Timely Dataflow uses an intricate distributed
protocol for tracking the computation’s progress. We formalize this
progress tracking protocol and verify its safety. Our formalization is
described in detail in our forthcoming &lt;a
href=&#34;https://traytel.bitbucket.io/papers/itp21-progress_tracking/safe.pdf&#34;&gt;ITP&#39;21
paper&lt;/a&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Information Flow Control via Dependency Tracking</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/IFC_Tracking.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/IFC_Tracking.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Benedikt Nordhoff       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We provide a characterisation of how information is propagated by
program executions based on the tracking data and control dependencies
within executions themselves.  The characterisation might be used for
deriving approximative safety properties to be targeted by static
analyses or checked at runtime.  We utilise a simple yet versatile
control flow graph model as a program representation.  As our model is
not assumed to be finite it can be instantiated for a broad class of
programs.  The targeted security property is indistinguishable
security where executions produce sequences of observations and only
non-terminating executions are allowed to drop a tail of those.  A
very crude approximation of our characterisation is slicing based on
program dependence graphs, which we use as a minimal example and
derive a corresponding soundness result.  For further details and
applications refer to the authors upcoming dissertation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Grothendieck's Schemes in Algebraic Geometry</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Grothendieck_Schemes.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Grothendieck_Schemes.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Anthony Bordg, Lawrence Paulson, Wenda Li       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>29 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We formalize mainstream structures in algebraic geometry culminating
in Grothendieck&#39;s schemes: presheaves of rings, sheaves of rings,
ringed spaces, locally ringed spaces, affine schemes and schemes. We
prove that the spectrum of a ring is a locally ringed space, hence an
affine scheme. Finally, we prove that any affine scheme is a scheme.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Constructive Cryptography in HOL: the Communication Modeling Aspect</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Constructive_Cryptography_CM.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Constructive_Cryptography_CM.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Andreas Lochbihler, S. Reza Sefidgar       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
Constructive Cryptography (CC) [&lt;a
href=&#34;https://conference.iiis.tsinghua.edu.cn/ICS2011/content/papers/14.html&#34;&gt;ICS
2011&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-27375-9_3&#34;&gt;TOSCA
2011&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-662-53641-4_1&#34;&gt;TCC
2016&lt;/a&gt;] introduces an abstract approach to composable security
statements that allows one to focus on a particular aspect of security
proofs at a time. Instead of proving the properties of concrete
systems, CC studies system classes, i.e., the shared behavior of
similar systems, and their transformations.  Modeling of systems
communication plays a crucial role in composability and reusability of
security statements; yet, this aspect has not been studied in any of
the existing CC results. We extend our previous CC formalization
[&lt;a href=&#34;https://isa-afp.org/entries/Constructive_Cryptography.html&#34;&gt;Constructive_Cryptography&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/CSF.2019.00018&#34;&gt;CSF
2019&lt;/a&gt;] with a new semantic domain called Fused Resource
Templates (FRT) that abstracts over the systems communication patterns
in CC proofs. This widens the scope of cryptography proof
formalizations in the CryptHOL library [&lt;a
href=&#34;https://isa-afp.org/entries/CryptHOL.html&#34;&gt;CryptHOL&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-662-49498-1_20&#34;&gt;ESOP
2016&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s00145-019-09341-z&#34;&gt;J
Cryptol 2020&lt;/a&gt;].  This formalization is described in &lt;a
href=&#34;http://www.andreas-lochbihler.de/pub/basin2021.pdf&#34;&gt;Abstract
Modeling of Systems Communication in Constructive Cryptography using
CryptHOL&lt;/a&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Two algorithms based on modular arithmetic: lattice basis reduction and Hermite normal form computation</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Modular_arithmetic_LLL_and_HNF_algorithms.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Modular_arithmetic_LLL_and_HNF_algorithms.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Ralph Bottesch, Jose Divasón, René Thiemann       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>12 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We verify two algorithms for which modular arithmetic plays an
essential role: Storjohann&#39;s variant of the LLL lattice basis
reduction algorithm and Kopparty&#39;s algorithm for computing the
Hermite normal form of a matrix. To do this, we also formalize some
facts about the modulo operation with symmetric range. Our
implementations are based on the original papers, but are otherwise
efficient. For basis reduction we formalize two versions: one that
includes all of the optimizations/heuristics from Storjohann&#39;s
paper, and one excluding a heuristic that we observed to often
decrease efficiency. We also provide a fast, self-contained certifier
for basis reduction, based on the efficient Hermite normal form
algorithm.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Quantum projective measurements and the CHSH inequality</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Projective_Measurements.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Projective_Measurements.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mnacho Echenim       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This work contains a formalization of quantum projective measurements,
also known as von Neumann measurements, which are based on elements of
spectral theory. We also formalized the CHSH inequality, an inequality
involving expectations in a probability space that is violated by
quantum measurements, thus proving that quantum mechanics cannot be modeled with an underlying local hidden-variable theory.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>The Hermite–Lindemann–Weierstraß Transcendence Theorem</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Hermite_Lindemann.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Hermite_Lindemann.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Manuel Eberl       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&lt;p&gt;This article provides a formalisation of the
Hermite-Lindemann-Weierstraß Theorem (also known as simply
Hermite-Lindemann or Lindemann-Weierstraß). This theorem is one of the
crowning achievements of 19th century number theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theorem states that if $\alpha_1, \ldots,
\alpha_n\in\mathbb{C}$ are algebraic numbers that are linearly
independent over $\mathbb{Z}$, then $e^{\alpha_1},\ldots,e^{\alpha_n}$
are algebraically independent over $\mathbb{Q}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the &lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-66107-0_5&#34;&gt;previous
formalisation in Coq by Bernard&lt;/a&gt;, I proceeded by formalising
&lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511565977&#34;&gt;Baker&#39;s
version of the theorem and proof&lt;/a&gt; and then deriving the
original one from that. Baker&#39;s version states that for any
algebraic numbers $\beta_1, \ldots, \beta_n\in\mathbb{C}$ and distinct
algebraic numbers $\alpha_i, \ldots, \alpha_n\in\mathbb{C}$, we have
$\beta_1 e^{\alpha_1} + \ldots + \beta_n e^{\alpha_n} = 0$ if and only
if all the $\beta_i$ are zero.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This has a number of
direct corollaries, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;$e$ and $\pi$
are transcendental&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;$e^z$, $\sin z$, $\tan z$,
etc. are transcendental for algebraic
$z\in\mathbb{C}\setminus\{0\}$&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;$\ln z$ is
transcendental for algebraic $z\in\mathbb{C}\setminus\{0,
1\}$&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Mereology</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Mereology.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Mereology.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Ben Blumson       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We use Isabelle/HOL to verify elementary theorems and alternative
axiomatizations of classical extensional mereology.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>The Sunflower Lemma of Erdős and Rado</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Sunflowers.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Sunflowers.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> René Thiemann       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>25 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We formally define sunflowers and provide a formalization of the
sunflower lemma of Erd&amp;odblac;s and Rado: whenever a set of
size-&lt;i&gt;k&lt;/i&gt;-sets has a larger cardinality than
&lt;i&gt;(r - 1)&lt;sup&gt;k&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;middot; k!&lt;/i&gt;,
then it contains a sunflower of cardinality &lt;i&gt;r&lt;/i&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>A Verified Imperative Implementation of B-Trees</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/BTree.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/BTree.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Niels Mündler       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In this work, we use the interactive theorem prover Isabelle/HOL to
verify an imperative implementation of the classical B-tree data
structure invented by Bayer and McCreight [ACM 1970]. The
implementation supports set membership and insertion queries with
efficient binary search for intra-node navigation. This is
accomplished by first specifying the structure abstractly in the
functional modeling language HOL and proving functional correctness.
Using manual refinement, we derive an imperative implementation in
Imperative/HOL. We show the validity of this refinement using the
separation logic utilities from the &lt;a
href=&#34;https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Refine_Imperative_HOL.html&#34;&gt;
Isabelle Refinement Framework &lt;/a&gt; . The code can be exported to
the programming languages SML and Scala. We examine the runtime of all
operations indirectly by reproducing results of the logarithmic
relationship between height and the number of nodes.  The results are
discussed in greater detail in the corresponding &lt;a
href=&#34;https://mediatum.ub.tum.de/1596550&#34;&gt;Bachelor&#39;s
Thesis&lt;/a&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Formal Puiseux Series</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Formal_Puiseux_Series.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Formal_Puiseux_Series.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Manuel Eberl       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&lt;p&gt;Formal Puiseux series are generalisations of formal power
series and formal Laurent series that also allow for fractional
exponents. They have the following general form: \[\sum_{i=N}^\infty
a_{i/d} X^{i/d}\] where &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; is an integer and
&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; is a positive integer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This
entry defines these series including their basic algebraic properties.
Furthermore, it proves the Newton–Puiseux Theorem, namely that the
Puiseux series over an algebraically closed field of characteristic 0
are also algebraically closed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>The Laws of Large Numbers</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Laws_of_Large_Numbers.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Laws_of_Large_Numbers.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Manuel Eberl       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>10 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&lt;p&gt;The Law of Large Numbers states that, informally, if one
performs a random experiment $X$ many times and takes the average of
the results, that average will be very close to the expected value
$E[X]$.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; More formally, let
$(X_i)_{i\in\mathbb{N}}$ be a sequence of independently identically
distributed random variables whose expected value $E[X_1]$ exists.
Denote the running average of $X_1, \ldots, X_n$ as $\overline{X}_n$.
Then:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Weak Law of Large Numbers
states that $\overline{X}_{n} \longrightarrow E[X_1]$ in probability
for $n\to\infty$, i.e. $\mathcal{P}(|\overline{X}_{n} - E[X_1]| &gt;
\varepsilon) \longrightarrow 0$ as $n\to\infty$ for any $\varepsilon
&gt; 0$.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Strong Law of Large Numbers states
that $\overline{X}_{n} \longrightarrow E[X_1]$ almost surely for
$n\to\infty$, i.e. $\mathcal{P}(\overline{X}_{n} \longrightarrow
E[X_1]) = 1$.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;In this entry, I
formally prove the strong law and from it the weak law. The approach
used for the proof of the strong law is a particularly quick and slick
one based on ergodic theory, which was formalised by Gouëzel in
another AFP entry.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Tarski's Parallel Postulate implies the 5th Postulate of Euclid, the Postulate of Playfair and the original Parallel Postulate of Euclid</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/IsaGeoCoq.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/IsaGeoCoq.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Roland Coghetto       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>31 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://geocoq.github.io/GeoCoq/&#34;&gt;GeoCoq library&lt;/a&gt;  contains a formalization
of geometry using the Coq proof assistant. It contains both proofs
about the foundations of geometry and high-level proofs in the same
style as in high school.  We port a part of the GeoCoq
2.4.0 library to Isabelle/HOL: more precisely,
the files Chap02.v to Chap13_3.v, suma.v as well as the associated
definitions and some useful files for the demonstration of certain
parallel postulates. The synthetic approach of the demonstrations is directly
inspired by those contained in GeoCoq. The names of the lemmas and
theorems used are kept as far as possible as well as the definitions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that T.J.M. Makarios has done
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Tarskis_Geometry.html&#34;&gt;some proofs in Tarski&#39;s Geometry&lt;/a&gt;. It uses a definition that does not quite
coincide with the definition used in Geocoq and here.
Furthermore, corresponding definitions in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Poincare_Disc.html&#34;&gt;Poincaré Disc Model
development&lt;/a&gt; are not identical to those defined in GeoCoq.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last part, it is
formalized that, in the neutral/absolute space, the axiom of the
parallels of Tarski&#39;s system implies the Playfair axiom, the 5th
postulate of Euclid and Euclid&#39;s original parallel postulate. These
proofs, which are not constructive, are directly inspired by Pierre
Boutry, Charly Gries, Julien Narboux and Pascal Schreck.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Solution to the xkcd Blue Eyes puzzle</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Blue_Eyes.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Blue_Eyes.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Jakub Kądziołka       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>30 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In a &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/blue_eyes.html&#34;&gt;puzzle published by
Randall Munroe&lt;/a&gt;, perfect logicians forbidden
from communicating are stranded on an island, and may only leave once
they have figured out their own eye color. We present a method of
modeling the behavior of perfect logicians and formalize a solution of
the puzzle.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Hood-Melville Queue</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Hood_Melville_Queue.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Hood_Melville_Queue.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Alejandro Gómez-Londoño       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This is a verified implementation of a constant time queue. The
original design is due to &lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/0020-0190(81)90030-2&#34;&gt;Hood
and Melville&lt;/a&gt;. This formalization follows the presentation in
&lt;em&gt;Purely Functional Data Structures&lt;/em&gt;by Okasaki.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>JinjaDCI: a Java semantics with dynamic class initialization</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/JinjaDCI.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/JinjaDCI.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Susannah Mansky       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We extend Jinja to include static fields, methods, and instructions,
and dynamic class initialization, based on the Java SE 8
specification. This includes extension of definitions and proofs. This
work is partially described in Mansky and Gunter&#39;s paper at CPP
2019 and Mansky&#39;s doctoral thesis (UIUC, 2020).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Cofinality and the Delta System Lemma</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Delta_System_Lemma.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Delta_System_Lemma.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Pedro Sánchez Terraf       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We formalize the basic results on cofinality of linearly ordered sets
and ordinals and Šanin’s Lemma for uncountable families of finite
sets. This last result is used to prove the countable chain condition
for Cohen posets. We work in the set theory framework of Isabelle/ZF,
using the Axiom of Choice as needed.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Topological semantics for paraconsistent and paracomplete logics</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Topological_Semantics.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Topological_Semantics.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> David Fuenmayor       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>17 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We introduce a generalized topological semantics for paraconsistent
and paracomplete logics by drawing upon early works on topological
Boolean algebras (cf. works by Kuratowski, Zarycki, McKinsey &amp;
Tarski, etc.). In particular, this work exemplarily illustrates the
shallow semantical embeddings approach (&lt;a
href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11787-012-0052-y&#34;&gt;SSE&lt;/a&gt;)
employing the proof assistant Isabelle/HOL. By means of the SSE
technique we can effectively harness theorem provers, model finders
and &#39;hammers&#39; for reasoning with quantified non-classical
logics.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Relational Minimum Spanning Tree Algorithms</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Relational_Minimum_Spanning_Trees.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Relational_Minimum_Spanning_Trees.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Walter Guttmann, Nicolas Robinson-O'Brien       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>08 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We verify the correctness of Prim&#39;s, Kruskal&#39;s and
Borůvka&#39;s minimum spanning tree algorithms based on algebras for
aggregation and minimisation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Inline Caching and Unboxing Optimization for Interpreters</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Interpreter_Optimizations.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Interpreter_Optimizations.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Martin Desharnais       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This Isabelle/HOL formalization builds on the
&lt;em&gt;VeriComp&lt;/em&gt; entry of the &lt;em&gt;Archive of Formal
Proofs&lt;/em&gt; to provide the following contributions:  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an operational semantics for a realistic virtual machine
(Std) for dynamically typed programming languages;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the formalization of an inline caching optimization (Inca),
a proof of bisimulation with (Std), and a compilation
function;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;the formalization of an unboxing
optimization (Ubx), a proof of bisimulation with (Inca), and a simple
compilation function.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;  This formalization was
described in the CPP 2021 paper &lt;em&gt;Towards Efficient and
Verified Virtual Machines for Dynamic Languages&lt;/em&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>The Relational Method with Message Anonymity for the Verification of Cryptographic Protocols</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Relational_Method.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Relational_Method.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Pasquale Noce       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>05 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This paper introduces a new method for the formal verification of
cryptographic protocols, the relational method, derived from
Paulson&#39;s inductive method by means of some enhancements aimed at
streamlining formal definitions and proofs, specially for protocols
using public key cryptography. Moreover, this paper proposes a method
to formalize a further security property, message anonymity, in
addition to message confidentiality and authenticity.  The relational
method, including message anonymity, is then applied to the
verification of a sample authentication protocol, comprising Password
Authenticated Connection Establishment (PACE) with Chip Authentication
Mapping followed by the explicit verification of an additional
password over the PACE secure channel.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Isabelle Marries Dirac: a Library for Quantum Computation and Quantum Information</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Isabelle_Marries_Dirac.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Isabelle_Marries_Dirac.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Anthony Bordg, Hanna Lachnitt, Yijun He       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>22 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This work is an effort to formalise some quantum algorithms and
results in quantum information theory. Formal methods being critical
for the safety and security of algorithms and protocols, we foresee
their widespread use for quantum computing in the future. We have
developed a large library for quantum computing in Isabelle based on a
matrix representation for quantum circuits, successfully formalising
the no-cloning theorem, quantum teleportation, Deutsch&#39;s
algorithm, the Deutsch-Jozsa algorithm and the quantum Prisoner&#39;s
Dilemma.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>The HOL-CSP Refinement Toolkit</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/CSP_RefTK.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/CSP_RefTK.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Safouan Taha, Burkhart Wolff, Lina Ye       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>19 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We use a formal development for CSP, called HOL-CSP2.0, to analyse a
family of refinement notions, comprising classic and new ones. This
analysis enables to derive a number of properties that allow to deepen
the understanding of these notions, in particular with respect to
specification decomposition principles for the case of infinite sets
of events. The established relations between the refinement relations
help to clarify some obscure points in the CSP literature, but also
provide a weapon for shorter refinement proofs. Furthermore, we
provide a framework for state-normalisation allowing to formally
reason on parameterised process architectures. As a result, we have a
modern environment for formal proofs of concurrent systems that allow
for the combination of general infinite processes with locally finite
ones in a logically safe way. We demonstrate these
verification-techniques for classical, generalised examples: The
CopyBuffer for arbitrary data and the Dijkstra&#39;s Dining
Philosopher Problem of arbitrary size.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Verified SAT-Based AI Planning</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Verified_SAT_Based_AI_Planning.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Verified_SAT_Based_AI_Planning.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mohammad Abdulaziz, Friedrich Kurz       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We present an executable formally verified SAT encoding of classical
AI planning that is based on the encodings by Kautz and Selman and the
one by Rintanen et al. The encoding was experimentally tested and
shown to be usable for reasonably sized standard AI planning
benchmarks. We also use it as a reference to test a state-of-the-art
SAT-based planner, showing that it sometimes falsely claims that
problems have no solutions of certain lengths. The formalisation in
this submission was described in an independent publication.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>AI Planning Languages Semantics</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/AI_Planning_Languages_Semantics.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/AI_Planning_Languages_Semantics.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mohammad Abdulaziz, Peter Lammich       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This is an Isabelle/HOL formalisation of the semantics of the
multi-valued planning tasks language that is used by the planning
system Fast-Downward, the STRIPS fragment of the Planning Domain
Definition Language (PDDL), and the STRIPS soundness meta-theory
developed by Vladimir Lifschitz. It also contains formally verified
checkers for checking the well-formedness of problems specified in
either language as well the correctness of potential solutions. The
formalisation in this entry was described in an earlier publication.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>A Sound Type System for Physical Quantities, Units, and Measurements</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Physical_Quantities.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Physical_Quantities.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Simon Foster, Burkhart Wolff       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
The present Isabelle theory builds a formal model for both the
International System of Quantities (ISQ) and the International System
of Units (SI), which are both fundamental for physics and engineering.
Both the ISQ and the SI are deeply integrated into Isabelle&#39;s
type system. Quantities are parameterised by dimension types, which
correspond to base vectors, and thus only quantities of the same
dimension can be equated. Since the underlying &#34;algebra of
quantities&#34; induces congruences on quantity and SI types,
specific tactic support is developed to capture these. Our
construction is validated by a test-set of known equivalences between
both quantities and SI units. Moreover, the presented theory can be
used for type-safe conversions between the SI system and others, like
the British Imperial System (BIS).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Finite Map Extras</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Finite-Map-Extras.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Finite-Map-Extras.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Javier Díaz       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>12 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This entry includes useful syntactic sugar, new operators and functions, and
their associated lemmas for finite maps which currently are not
present in the standard Finite_Map theory.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>A Formal Model of the Safely Composable Document Object Model with Shadow Roots</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Shadow_SC_DOM.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Shadow_SC_DOM.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Achim D. Brucker, Michael Herzberg       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>28 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In this AFP entry, we extend our formalization of the safely
composable DOM with Shadow Roots. This is a proposal for Shadow Roots
with stricter safety guarantess than the standard compliant
formalization (see &#34;Shadow DOM&#34;). Shadow Roots are a recent
proposal of the web community to support a component-based development
approach for client-side web applications.  Shadow roots are a
significant extension to the DOM standard and, as web standards are
condemned to be backward compatible, such extensions often result in
complex specification that may contain unwanted subtleties that can be
detected by a formalization.  Our Isabelle/HOL formalization is, in
the sense of object-orientation, an extension of our formalization of
the core DOM and enjoys the same basic properties, i.e., it is
extensible, i.e., can be extended without the need of re-proving
already proven properties and executable, i.e., we can generate
executable code from our specification. We exploit the executability
to show that our formalization complies to the official standard of
the W3C, respectively, the WHATWG.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>A Formal Model of the Document Object Model with Shadow Roots</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Shadow_DOM.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Shadow_DOM.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Achim D. Brucker, Michael Herzberg       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>28 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In this AFP entry, we extend our formalization of the core DOM with
Shadow Roots. Shadow roots are a recent proposal of the web community
to support a component-based development approach for client-side web
applications.  Shadow roots are a significant extension to the DOM
standard and, as web standards are condemned to be backward
compatible, such extensions often result in complex specification that
may contain unwanted subtleties that can be detected by a
formalization.  Our Isabelle/HOL formalization is, in the sense of
object-orientation, an extension of our formalization of the core DOM
and enjoys the same basic properties, i.e., it is extensible, i.e.,
can be extended without the need of re-proving already proven
properties and executable, i.e., we can generate executable code from
our specification. We exploit the executability to show that our
formalization complies to the official standard of the W3C,
respectively, the WHATWG.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>A Formalization of Safely Composable Web Components</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/SC_DOM_Components.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/SC_DOM_Components.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Achim D. Brucker, Michael Herzberg       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>28 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
While the (safely composable) DOM with shadow trees provide the
technical basis for defining web components, it does neither defines
the concept of web components nor specifies the safety properties that
web components should guarantee. Consequently, the standard also does
not discuss how or even if the methods for modifying the DOM respect
component boundaries. In AFP entry, we present a formally verified
model of safely composable web components and define safety properties
which ensure that different web components can only interact with each
other using well-defined interfaces. Moreover, our verification of the
application programming interface (API) of the DOM revealed numerous
invariants that implementations of the DOM API need to preserve to
ensure the integrity of components.  In comparison to the strict
standard compliance formalization of Web Components in the AFP entry
&#34;DOM_Components&#34;, the notion of components in this entry
(based on &#34;SC_DOM&#34; and &#34;Shadow_SC_DOM&#34;) provides
much stronger safety guarantees.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
