<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://www.isa-afp.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Archive of Formal Proofs</title>
    <link>https://www.isa-afp.org</link>
    <description>
      The Archive of Formal Proofs is a collection of proof libraries, examples,
      and larger scientific developments, mechanically checked
      in the theorem prover Isabelle.
    </description>
    <pubDate>07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <item>
       <title>Finitely Generated Abelian Groups</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Finitely_Generated_Abelian_Groups.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Finitely_Generated_Abelian_Groups.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Joseph Thommes, Manuel Eberl       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This article deals with the formalisation of some group-theoretic
results including the fundamental theorem of finitely generated
abelian groups characterising the structure of these groups as a
uniquely determined product of cyclic groups. Both the invariant
factor decomposition and the primary decomposition are covered.
Additional work includes results about the direct product, the
internal direct product and more group-theoretic lemmas.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>SpecCheck - Specification-Based Testing for Isabelle/ML</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/SpecCheck.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/SpecCheck.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Kevin Kappelmann, Lukas Bulwahn, Sebastian Willenbrink       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
SpecCheck is a &lt;a
href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/QuickCheck&#34;&gt;QuickCheck&lt;/a&gt;-like
testing framework for Isabelle/ML. You can use it to write
specifications for ML functions. SpecCheck then checks whether your
specification holds by testing your function against a given number of
generated inputs. It helps you to identify bugs by printing
counterexamples on failure and provides you timing information.
SpecCheck is customisable and allows you to specify your own input
generators, test output formats, as well as pretty printers and
shrinking functions for counterexamples among other things.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Van der Waerden's Theorem</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Van_der_Waerden.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Van_der_Waerden.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Katharina Kreuzer, Manuel Eberl       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>22 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This article formalises the proof of Van der Waerden&#39;s Theorem
from Ramsey theory.  Van der Waerden&#39;s Theorem states that for
integers $k$ and $l$ there exists a number $N$ which guarantees that
if an integer interval of length at least $N$ is coloured with $k$
colours, there will always be an arithmetic progression of length $l$
of the same colour in said interval. The proof goes along the lines of
\cite{Swan}.  The smallest number $N_{k,l}$ fulfilling Van der
Waerden&#39;s Theorem is then called the Van der Waerden Number.
Finding the Van der Waerden Number is still an open problem for most
values of $k$ and $l$.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>MiniSail - A kernel language for the ISA specification language SAIL</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/MiniSail.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/MiniSail.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mark Wassell       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>18 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
MiniSail is a kernel language for Sail, an instruction set
architecture (ISA) specification language. Sail is an imperative
language with a light-weight dependent type system similar to
refinement type systems. From an ISA specification, the Sail compiler
can generate theorem prover code and C (or OCaml) to give an
executable emulator for an architecture. The idea behind MiniSail is
to capture the key and novel features of Sail in terms of their
syntax, typing rules and operational semantics, and to confirm that
they work together by proving progress and preservation lemmas. We use
the Nominal2 library to handle binding.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Public Announcement Logic</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Public_Announcement_Logic.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Public_Announcement_Logic.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Asta Halkjær From       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>17 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This work is a formalization of public announcement logic with
countably many agents. It includes proofs of soundness and
completeness for a variant of the axiom system PA + DIST! + NEC!. The
completeness proof builds on the Epistemic Logic theory.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>A Shorter Compiler Correctness Proof for Language IMP</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/IMP_Compiler.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/IMP_Compiler.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Pasquale Noce       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>04 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This paper presents a compiler correctness proof for the didactic
imperative programming language IMP, introduced in Nipkow and
Klein&#39;s book on formal programming language semantics (version of
March 2021), whose size is just two thirds of the book&#39;s proof in
the number of formal text lines. As such, it promises to constitute a
further enhanced reference for the formal verification of compilers
meant for larger, real-world programming languages.  The presented
proof does not depend on language determinism, so that the proposed
approach can be applied to non-deterministic languages as well. As a
confirmation, this paper extends IMP with an additional
non-deterministic choice command, and proves compiler correctness,
viz. the simulation of compiled code execution by source code, for
such extended language.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Lyndon words</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Combinatorics_Words_Lyndon.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Combinatorics_Words_Lyndon.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Štěpán Holub, Štěpán Starosta       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>24 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
Lyndon words are words lexicographically minimal in their conjugacy
class. We formalize their basic properties and characterizations, in
particular the concepts of the longest Lyndon suffix and the Lyndon
factorization. Most of the work assumes a fixed lexicographical order.
Nevertheless we also define the smallest relation guaranteeing
lexicographical minimality of a given word (in its conjugacy class).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Graph Lemma</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Combinatorics_Words_Graph_Lemma.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Combinatorics_Words_Graph_Lemma.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Štěpán Holub, Štěpán Starosta       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>24 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
Graph lemma quantifies the defect effect of a system of word
equations. That is, it provides an upper bound on the rank of the
system. We formalize the proof based on the decomposition of a
solution into its free basis. A direct application is an alternative
proof of the fact that two noncommuting words form a code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Combinatorics on Words Basics</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Combinatorics_Words.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Combinatorics_Words.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Štěpán Holub, Martin Raška, Štěpán Starosta       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>24 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We formalize basics of Combinatorics on Words. This is an extension of
existing theories on lists. We provide additional properties related
to prefix, suffix, factor, length and rotation. The topics include
prefix and suffix comparability, mismatch, word power, total and
reversed morphisms, border, periods, primitivity and roots. We also
formalize basic, mostly folklore results related to word equations:
equidivisibility, commutation and conjugation. Slightly advanced
properties include the Periodicity lemma (often cited as the Fine and
Wilf theorem) and the variant of the Lyndon-Schützenberger theorem for
words. We support the algebraic point of view which sees words as
generators of submonoids of a free monoid. This leads to the concepts
of the (free) hull, the (free) basis (or code).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Regression Test Selection</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Regression_Test_Selection.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Regression_Test_Selection.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Susannah Mansky       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This development provides a general definition for safe Regression
Test Selection (RTS) algorithms. RTS algorithms select which tests to
rerun on revised code, reducing the time required to check for newly
introduced errors. An RTS algorithm is considered safe if and only if
all deselected tests would have unchanged results.  This definition is
instantiated with two class-collection-based RTS algorithms run over
the JVM as modeled by JinjaDCI. This is achieved with a general
definition for Collection Semantics, small-step semantics instrumented
to collect information during execution. As the RTS definition
mandates safety, these instantiations include proofs of safety.  This
work is described in Mansky and Gunter&#39;s LSFA 2020 paper and
Mansky&#39;s doctoral thesis (UIUC, 2020).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Isabelle's Metalogic: Formalization and Proof Checker</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Metalogic_ProofChecker.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Metalogic_ProofChecker.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Tobias Nipkow, Simon Roßkopf       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In this entry we formalize Isabelle&#39;s metalogic in Isabelle/HOL.
Furthermore, we define a language of proof terms and an executable
proof checker and prove its soundness wrt. the metalogic.  The
formalization is intentionally kept close to the Isabelle
implementation(for example using de Brujin indices) to enable easy
integration of generated code with the Isabelle system without a
complicated translation layer.  The formalization is described in our
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2104.12224.pdf&#34;&gt;CADE 28 paper&lt;/a&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Lifting the Exponent</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Lifting_the_Exponent.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Lifting_the_Exponent.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Jakub Kądziołka       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We formalize the &lt;i&gt;Lifting the Exponent Lemma&lt;/i&gt;, which
shows how to find the largest power of $p$ dividing $a^n \pm b^n$, for
a prime $p$ and positive integers $a$ and $b$. The proof follows &lt;a
href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/aops-cdn.artofproblemsolving.com/resources/articles/lifting-the-exponent.pdf&#34;&gt;Amir Hossein Parvardi&#39;s&lt;/a&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>The BKR Decision Procedure for Univariate Real Arithmetic</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/BenOr_Kozen_Reif.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/BenOr_Kozen_Reif.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Katherine Cordwell, Yong Kiam Tan, André Platzer       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>24 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We formalize the univariate case of Ben-Or, Kozen, and Reif&#39;s
decision procedure for first-order real arithmetic (the BKR
algorithm). We also formalize the univariate case of Renegar&#39;s
variation of the BKR algorithm. The two formalizations differ
mathematically in minor ways (that have significant impact on the
multivariate case), but are quite similar in proof structure.  Both
rely on sign-determination (finding the set of consistent sign
assignments for a set of polynomials).  The method used for
sign-determination is similar to Tarski&#39;s original quantifier
elimination algorithm (it stores key information in a matrix
equation), but with a reduction step to keep complexity low.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Gale-Stewart Games</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/GaleStewart_Games.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/GaleStewart_Games.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Sebastiaan Joosten       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This is a formalisation of the main result of Gale and Stewart from
1953, showing that closed finite games are determined. This property
is now known as the Gale Stewart Theorem. While the original paper
shows some additional theorems as well, we only formalize this main
result, but do so in a somewhat general way. We formalize games of a
fixed arbitrary length, including infinite length, using co-inductive
lists, and show that defensive strategies exist unless the other
player is winning. For closed games, defensive strategies are winning
for the closed player, proving that such games are determined. For
finite games, which are a special case in our formalisation, all games
are closed.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Formalization of Timely Dataflow's Progress Tracking Protocol</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Progress_Tracking.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Progress_Tracking.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Matthias Brun, Sára Decova, Andrea Lattuada, Dmitriy Traytel       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
Large-scale stream processing systems often follow the dataflow
paradigm, which enforces a program structure that exposes a high
degree of parallelism. The Timely Dataflow distributed system supports
expressive cyclic dataflows for which it offers low-latency data- and
pipeline-parallel stream processing. To achieve high expressiveness
and performance, Timely Dataflow uses an intricate distributed
protocol for tracking the computation’s progress. We formalize this
progress tracking protocol and verify its safety. Our formalization is
described in detail in our forthcoming &lt;a
href=&#34;https://traytel.bitbucket.io/papers/itp21-progress_tracking/safe.pdf&#34;&gt;ITP&#39;21
paper&lt;/a&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Information Flow Control via Dependency Tracking</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/IFC_Tracking.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/IFC_Tracking.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Benedikt Nordhoff       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We provide a characterisation of how information is propagated by
program executions based on the tracking data and control dependencies
within executions themselves.  The characterisation might be used for
deriving approximative safety properties to be targeted by static
analyses or checked at runtime.  We utilise a simple yet versatile
control flow graph model as a program representation.  As our model is
not assumed to be finite it can be instantiated for a broad class of
programs.  The targeted security property is indistinguishable
security where executions produce sequences of observations and only
non-terminating executions are allowed to drop a tail of those.  A
very crude approximation of our characterisation is slicing based on
program dependence graphs, which we use as a minimal example and
derive a corresponding soundness result.  For further details and
applications refer to the authors upcoming dissertation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Grothendieck's Schemes in Algebraic Geometry</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Grothendieck_Schemes.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Grothendieck_Schemes.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Anthony Bordg, Lawrence Paulson, Wenda Li       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>29 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We formalize mainstream structures in algebraic geometry culminating
in Grothendieck&#39;s schemes: presheaves of rings, sheaves of rings,
ringed spaces, locally ringed spaces, affine schemes and schemes. We
prove that the spectrum of a ring is a locally ringed space, hence an
affine scheme. Finally, we prove that any affine scheme is a scheme.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Hensel's Lemma for the p-adic Integers</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Padic_Ints.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Padic_Ints.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Aaron Crighton       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We formalize the ring of &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;-adic integers within the framework of the
HOL-Algebra library. The carrier of the ring is formalized as the
inverse limit of quotients of the integers by powers of a fixed prime
&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;. We define an integer-valued valuation, as well as an
extended-integer valued valuation which sends 0 to the infinite
element. Basic topological facts about the &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;-adic integers are
formalized, including completeness and sequential compactness. Taylor
expansions of polynomials over a commutative ring are defined,
culminating in the formalization of Hensel&#39;s Lemma based on a
proof due to Keith Conrad.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Constructive Cryptography in HOL: the Communication Modeling Aspect</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Constructive_Cryptography_CM.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Constructive_Cryptography_CM.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Andreas Lochbihler, S. Reza Sefidgar       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
Constructive Cryptography (CC) [&lt;a
href=&#34;https://conference.iiis.tsinghua.edu.cn/ICS2011/content/papers/14.html&#34;&gt;ICS
2011&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-27375-9_3&#34;&gt;TOSCA
2011&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-662-53641-4_1&#34;&gt;TCC
2016&lt;/a&gt;] introduces an abstract approach to composable security
statements that allows one to focus on a particular aspect of security
proofs at a time. Instead of proving the properties of concrete
systems, CC studies system classes, i.e., the shared behavior of
similar systems, and their transformations.  Modeling of systems
communication plays a crucial role in composability and reusability of
security statements; yet, this aspect has not been studied in any of
the existing CC results. We extend our previous CC formalization
[&lt;a href=&#34;https://isa-afp.org/entries/Constructive_Cryptography.html&#34;&gt;Constructive_Cryptography&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/CSF.2019.00018&#34;&gt;CSF
2019&lt;/a&gt;] with a new semantic domain called Fused Resource
Templates (FRT) that abstracts over the systems communication patterns
in CC proofs. This widens the scope of cryptography proof
formalizations in the CryptHOL library [&lt;a
href=&#34;https://isa-afp.org/entries/CryptHOL.html&#34;&gt;CryptHOL&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-662-49498-1_20&#34;&gt;ESOP
2016&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s00145-019-09341-z&#34;&gt;J
Cryptol 2020&lt;/a&gt;].  This formalization is described in &lt;a
href=&#34;http://www.andreas-lochbihler.de/pub/basin2021.pdf&#34;&gt;Abstract
Modeling of Systems Communication in Constructive Cryptography using
CryptHOL&lt;/a&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Two algorithms based on modular arithmetic: lattice basis reduction and Hermite normal form computation</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Modular_arithmetic_LLL_and_HNF_algorithms.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Modular_arithmetic_LLL_and_HNF_algorithms.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Ralph Bottesch, Jose Divasón, René Thiemann       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>12 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We verify two algorithms for which modular arithmetic plays an
essential role: Storjohann&#39;s variant of the LLL lattice basis
reduction algorithm and Kopparty&#39;s algorithm for computing the
Hermite normal form of a matrix. To do this, we also formalize some
facts about the modulo operation with symmetric range. Our
implementations are based on the original papers, but are otherwise
efficient. For basis reduction we formalize two versions: one that
includes all of the optimizations/heuristics from Storjohann&#39;s
paper, and one excluding a heuristic that we observed to often
decrease efficiency. We also provide a fast, self-contained certifier
for basis reduction, based on the efficient Hermite normal form
algorithm.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Quantum projective measurements and the CHSH inequality</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Projective_Measurements.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Projective_Measurements.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mnacho Echenim       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This work contains a formalization of quantum projective measurements,
also known as von Neumann measurements, which are based on elements of
spectral theory. We also formalized the CHSH inequality, an inequality
involving expectations in a probability space that is violated by
quantum measurements, thus proving that quantum mechanics cannot be modeled with an underlying local hidden-variable theory.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>The Hermite–Lindemann–Weierstraß Transcendence Theorem</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Hermite_Lindemann.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Hermite_Lindemann.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Manuel Eberl       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&lt;p&gt;This article provides a formalisation of the
Hermite-Lindemann-Weierstraß Theorem (also known as simply
Hermite-Lindemann or Lindemann-Weierstraß). This theorem is one of the
crowning achievements of 19th century number theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theorem states that if $\alpha_1, \ldots,
\alpha_n\in\mathbb{C}$ are algebraic numbers that are linearly
independent over $\mathbb{Z}$, then $e^{\alpha_1},\ldots,e^{\alpha_n}$
are algebraically independent over $\mathbb{Q}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the &lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-66107-0_5&#34;&gt;previous
formalisation in Coq by Bernard&lt;/a&gt;, I proceeded by formalising
&lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511565977&#34;&gt;Baker&#39;s
version of the theorem and proof&lt;/a&gt; and then deriving the
original one from that. Baker&#39;s version states that for any
algebraic numbers $\beta_1, \ldots, \beta_n\in\mathbb{C}$ and distinct
algebraic numbers $\alpha_i, \ldots, \alpha_n\in\mathbb{C}$, we have
$\beta_1 e^{\alpha_1} + \ldots + \beta_n e^{\alpha_n} = 0$ if and only
if all the $\beta_i$ are zero.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This has a number of
direct corollaries, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;$e$ and $\pi$
are transcendental&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;$e^z$, $\sin z$, $\tan z$,
etc. are transcendental for algebraic
$z\in\mathbb{C}\setminus\{0\}$&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;$\ln z$ is
transcendental for algebraic $z\in\mathbb{C}\setminus\{0,
1\}$&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Mereology</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Mereology.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Mereology.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Ben Blumson       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We use Isabelle/HOL to verify elementary theorems and alternative
axiomatizations of classical extensional mereology.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>The Sunflower Lemma of Erdős and Rado</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Sunflowers.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Sunflowers.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> René Thiemann       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>25 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We formally define sunflowers and provide a formalization of the
sunflower lemma of Erd&amp;odblac;s and Rado: whenever a set of
size-&lt;i&gt;k&lt;/i&gt;-sets has a larger cardinality than
&lt;i&gt;(r - 1)&lt;sup&gt;k&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;middot; k!&lt;/i&gt;,
then it contains a sunflower of cardinality &lt;i&gt;r&lt;/i&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>A Verified Imperative Implementation of B-Trees</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/BTree.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/BTree.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Niels Mündler       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In this work, we use the interactive theorem prover Isabelle/HOL to
verify an imperative implementation of the classical B-tree data
structure invented by Bayer and McCreight [ACM 1970]. The
implementation supports set membership and insertion queries with
efficient binary search for intra-node navigation. This is
accomplished by first specifying the structure abstractly in the
functional modeling language HOL and proving functional correctness.
Using manual refinement, we derive an imperative implementation in
Imperative/HOL. We show the validity of this refinement using the
separation logic utilities from the &lt;a
href=&#34;https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Refine_Imperative_HOL.html&#34;&gt;
Isabelle Refinement Framework &lt;/a&gt; . The code can be exported to
the programming languages SML and Scala. We examine the runtime of all
operations indirectly by reproducing results of the logarithmic
relationship between height and the number of nodes.  The results are
discussed in greater detail in the corresponding &lt;a
href=&#34;https://mediatum.ub.tum.de/1596550&#34;&gt;Bachelor&#39;s
Thesis&lt;/a&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Formal Puiseux Series</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Formal_Puiseux_Series.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Formal_Puiseux_Series.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Manuel Eberl       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&lt;p&gt;Formal Puiseux series are generalisations of formal power
series and formal Laurent series that also allow for fractional
exponents. They have the following general form: \[\sum_{i=N}^\infty
a_{i/d} X^{i/d}\] where &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; is an integer and
&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; is a positive integer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This
entry defines these series including their basic algebraic properties.
Furthermore, it proves the Newton–Puiseux Theorem, namely that the
Puiseux series over an algebraically closed field of characteristic 0
are also algebraically closed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>The Laws of Large Numbers</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Laws_of_Large_Numbers.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Laws_of_Large_Numbers.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Manuel Eberl       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>10 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&lt;p&gt;The Law of Large Numbers states that, informally, if one
performs a random experiment $X$ many times and takes the average of
the results, that average will be very close to the expected value
$E[X]$.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt; More formally, let
$(X_i)_{i\in\mathbb{N}}$ be a sequence of independently identically
distributed random variables whose expected value $E[X_1]$ exists.
Denote the running average of $X_1, \ldots, X_n$ as $\overline{X}_n$.
Then:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Weak Law of Large Numbers
states that $\overline{X}_{n} \longrightarrow E[X_1]$ in probability
for $n\to\infty$, i.e. $\mathcal{P}(|\overline{X}_{n} - E[X_1]| &gt;
\varepsilon) \longrightarrow 0$ as $n\to\infty$ for any $\varepsilon
&gt; 0$.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;The Strong Law of Large Numbers states
that $\overline{X}_{n} \longrightarrow E[X_1]$ almost surely for
$n\to\infty$, i.e. $\mathcal{P}(\overline{X}_{n} \longrightarrow
E[X_1]) = 1$.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;In this entry, I
formally prove the strong law and from it the weak law. The approach
used for the proof of the strong law is a particularly quick and slick
one based on ergodic theory, which was formalised by Gouëzel in
another AFP entry.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Tarski's Parallel Postulate implies the 5th Postulate of Euclid, the Postulate of Playfair and the original Parallel Postulate of Euclid</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/IsaGeoCoq.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/IsaGeoCoq.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Roland Coghetto       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>31 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://geocoq.github.io/GeoCoq/&#34;&gt;GeoCoq library&lt;/a&gt;  contains a formalization
of geometry using the Coq proof assistant. It contains both proofs
about the foundations of geometry and high-level proofs in the same
style as in high school.  We port a part of the GeoCoq
2.4.0 library to Isabelle/HOL: more precisely,
the files Chap02.v to Chap13_3.v, suma.v as well as the associated
definitions and some useful files for the demonstration of certain
parallel postulates. The synthetic approach of the demonstrations is directly
inspired by those contained in GeoCoq. The names of the lemmas and
theorems used are kept as far as possible as well as the definitions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that T.J.M. Makarios has done
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Tarskis_Geometry.html&#34;&gt;some proofs in Tarski&#39;s Geometry&lt;/a&gt;. It uses a definition that does not quite
coincide with the definition used in Geocoq and here.
Furthermore, corresponding definitions in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Poincare_Disc.html&#34;&gt;Poincaré Disc Model
development&lt;/a&gt; are not identical to those defined in GeoCoq.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last part, it is
formalized that, in the neutral/absolute space, the axiom of the
parallels of Tarski&#39;s system implies the Playfair axiom, the 5th
postulate of Euclid and Euclid&#39;s original parallel postulate. These
proofs, which are not constructive, are directly inspired by Pierre
Boutry, Charly Gries, Julien Narboux and Pascal Schreck.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Solution to the xkcd Blue Eyes puzzle</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Blue_Eyes.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Blue_Eyes.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Jakub Kądziołka       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>30 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In a &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/blue_eyes.html&#34;&gt;puzzle published by
Randall Munroe&lt;/a&gt;, perfect logicians forbidden
from communicating are stranded on an island, and may only leave once
they have figured out their own eye color. We present a method of
modeling the behavior of perfect logicians and formalize a solution of
the puzzle.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Hood-Melville Queue</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Hood_Melville_Queue.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Hood_Melville_Queue.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Alejandro Gómez-Londoño       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This is a verified implementation of a constant time queue. The
original design is due to &lt;a
href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/0020-0190(81)90030-2&#34;&gt;Hood
and Melville&lt;/a&gt;. This formalization follows the presentation in
&lt;em&gt;Purely Functional Data Structures&lt;/em&gt;by Okasaki.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
