<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://www.isa-afp.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Archive of Formal Proofs</title>
    <link>https://www.isa-afp.org</link>
    <description>
      The Archive of Formal Proofs is a collection of proof libraries, examples,
      and larger scientific developments, mechanically checked
      in the theorem prover Isabelle.
    </description>
    <pubDate>29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <item>
       <title>Simplicial Complexes and Boolean functions</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Simplicial_complexes_and_boolean_functions.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Simplicial_complexes_and_boolean_functions.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Jesús Aransay, Alejandro del Campo, Julius Michaelis       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>29 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In this work we formalise the isomorphism between simplicial complexes
of dimension $n$ and monotone Boolean functions in $n$ variables,
mainly following the definitions and results as introduced by N. A.
Scoville. We also take advantage of the AFP
representation of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/ROBDD.html&#34;&gt;ROBDD&lt;/a&gt;
(Reduced Ordered Binary Decision Diagrams) to compute the ROBDD representation of a
given simplicial complex (by means of the isomorphism to Boolean
functions). Some examples of simplicial complexes and associated
Boolean functions are also presented.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>van Emde Boas Trees</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Van_Emde_Boas_Trees.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Van_Emde_Boas_Trees.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Thomas Ammer, Peter Lammich       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>23 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
The &lt;em&gt;van Emde Boas tree&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;van Emde Boas
priority queue&lt;/em&gt; is a data structure supporting membership
test, insertion, predecessor and successor search, minimum and maximum
determination and deletion in &lt;em&gt;O(log log U)&lt;/em&gt; time, where &lt;em&gt;U =
0,...,2&lt;sup&gt;n-1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is the overall range to be
considered. &lt;p/&gt; The presented formalization follows Chapter 20
of the popular &lt;em&gt;Introduction to Algorithms (3rd
ed.)&lt;/em&gt; by Cormen, Leiserson, Rivest and Stein (CLRS),
extending the list of formally verified CLRS algorithms. Our current
formalization is based on the first author&#39;s bachelor&#39;s
thesis. &lt;p/&gt; First, we prove correct a
&lt;em&gt;functional&lt;/em&gt; implementation, w.r.t. an abstract
data type for sets. Apart from functional correctness, we show a
resource bound, and runtime bounds w.r.t. manually defined timing
functions for the operations. &lt;p/&gt; Next, we refine the
operations to Imperative HOL with time, and show correctness and
complexity. This yields a practically more efficient implementation,
and eliminates the manually defined timing functions from the trusted
base of the proof.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Foundation of geometry in planes, and some complements: Excluding the parallel axioms</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Foundation_of_geometry.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Foundation_of_geometry.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Fumiya Iwama       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&#34;Foundations of Geometry&#34; is a mathematical book written by
Hilbert in 1899. This entry is a complete formalization of
&#34;Incidence&#34; (excluding cubic axioms), &#34;Order&#34; and
&#34;Congruence&#34; (excluding point sequences) of the axioms
constructed in this book. In addition, the theorem of the problem
about the part that is treated implicitly and is not clearly stated in
it is being carried out in parallel.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>The Hahn and Jordan Decomposition Theorems</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Hahn_Jordan_Decomposition.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Hahn_Jordan_Decomposition.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Marie Cousin, Mnacho Echenim, Hervé Guiol       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In this work we formalize the Hahn decomposition theorem for signed
measures, namely that any measure space for a signed measure can be
decomposed into a positive and a negative set, where every measurable
subset of the positive one has a positive measure, and every
measurable subset of the negative one has a negative measure. We also
formalize the Jordan decomposition theorem as a corollary, which
states that the signed measure under consideration admits a unique
decomposition into a difference of two positive measures, at least one
of which is finite.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Exploring Simplified Variants of Gödel’s Ontological Argument in Isabelle/HOL</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/SimplifiedOntologicalArgument.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/SimplifiedOntologicalArgument.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Christoph Benzmüller       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>08 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&lt;p&gt;Simplified variants of Gödel&#39;s ontological argument are
explored. Among those is a particularly interesting simplified
argument which is (i) valid already in basic
modal logics K or KT, (ii) which does not suffer from modal collapse,
and (iii) which avoids the rather complex predicates of essence (Ess.)
and necessary existence (NE) as used by Gödel.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Whether the presented variants increase or decrease the
attractiveness and persuasiveness of the ontological argument is a
question I would like to pass on to philosophy and theology.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Real Exponents as the Limits of Sequences of Rational Exponents</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Real_Power.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Real_Power.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Jacques D. Fleuriot       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>08 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In this formalisation, we  construct real exponents as the limits of
sequences of rational exponents. In particular, if $a \ge 1$ and $x
\in \mathbb{R}$, we choose an increasing rational sequence $r_n$ such
that $\lim_{n\to\infty} {r_n} = x$. Then the sequence $a^{r_n}$ is
increasing and if $r$ is any rational number such that $r &gt; x$,
$a^{r_n}$ is bounded above by $a^r$. By the convergence criterion for
monotone sequences, $a^{r_n}$ converges. We define $a^ x =
\lim_{n\to\infty} a^{r_n}$ and show that it has the expected
properties (for $a \ge 0$).  This particular construction of real
exponents is needed instead of the usual one using the natural
logarithm and exponential functions (which already exists in Isabelle)
to support our mechanical derivation of Euler&#39;s exponential
series as an ``infinite polynomial&#34;. Aside from helping us avoid
circular reasoning, this is, as far as we are aware, the first time
real exponents are mechanised in this way within a proof assistant.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Automating Public Announcement Logic and the Wise Men Puzzle in Isabelle/HOL</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/PAL.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/PAL.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Christoph Benzmüller, Sebastian Reiche       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>08 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We present a shallow embedding of public announcement logic (PAL) with
relativized general knowledge in HOL. We then use PAL to obtain an
elegant encoding of the wise men puzzle, which we solve automatically
using sledgehammer.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Factorization of Polynomials with Algebraic Coefficients</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Factor_Algebraic_Polynomial.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Factor_Algebraic_Polynomial.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Manuel Eberl, René Thiemann       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>08 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
The AFP already contains a verified implementation of algebraic
numbers. However, it is has a severe limitation in its factorization
algorithm of real and complex polynomials: the factorization is only
guaranteed to succeed if the coefficients of the polynomial are
rational numbers. In this work, we verify an algorithm to factor all
real and complex polynomials whose coefficients are algebraic. The
existence of such an algorithm proves in a constructive way that the
set of complex algebraic numbers is algebraically closed. Internally,
the algorithm is based on resultants of multivariate polynomials and
an approximation algorithm using interval arithmetic.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Szemerédi's Regularity Lemma</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Szemeredi_Regularity.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Szemeredi_Regularity.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Chelsea Edmonds, Angeliki Koutsoukou-Argyraki, Lawrence C. Paulson       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>05 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&lt;a
href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Szemerédi_regularity_lemma&#34;&gt;Szemerédi&#39;s
regularity lemma&lt;/a&gt; is a key result in the study of large
graphs. It asserts the existence an upper bound on the number of parts
the vertices of a graph need to be partitioned into such that the
edges between the parts are random in a certain sense. This bound
depends only on the desired precision and not on the graph itself, in
the spirit of Ramsey&#39;s theorem. The formalisation follows online
course notes by &lt;a
href=&#34;https://www.dpmms.cam.ac.uk/~par31/notes/tic.pdf&#34;&gt;Tim
Gowers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
href=&#34;https://yufeizhao.com/gtac/gtac.pdf&#34;&gt;Yufei
Zhao&lt;/a&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Quantum and Classical Registers</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Registers.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Registers.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Dominique Unruh       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>28 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
A formalization of the theory of quantum and classical registers as
developed by (Unruh, Quantum and Classical Registers). In a nutshell,
a register refers to a part of a larger memory or system that can be
accessed independently.  Registers can be constructed from other
registers and several (compatible) registers can be composed. This
formalization develops both the generic theory of registers as well as
specific instantiations for classical and quantum registers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Belief Revision Theory</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Belief_Revision.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Belief_Revision.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Valentin Fouillard, Safouan Taha, Frédéric Boulanger, Nicolas Sabouret       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>19 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
The 1985 paper by Carlos Alchourrón, Peter Gärdenfors, and David
Makinson (AGM), “On the Logic of Theory Change: Partial Meet
Contraction and Revision Functions” launches a large and rapidly
growing literature that employs formal models and logics to handle
changing beliefs of a rational agent and to take into account new
piece of information observed by this agent. In 2011, a review book
titled &#34;AGM 25 Years: Twenty-Five Years of Research in Belief
Change&#34; was edited to summarize the first twenty five years of
works based on AGM.  This  HOL-based  AFP entry is a faithful
formalization of the AGM operators (e.g. contraction, revision,
remainder ...) axiomatized in the original paper. It also contains the
proofs of all the theorems stated in the paper that show how these
operators combine. Both proofs of Harper and Levi identities are
established.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>X86 instruction semantics and basic block symbolic execution</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/X86_Semantics.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/X86_Semantics.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Freek Verbeek, Abhijith Bharadwaj, Joshua Bockenek, Ian Roessle, Timmy Weerwag, Binoy Ravindran       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>13 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This AFP entry provides semantics for roughly 120 different X86-64
assembly instructions. These instructions include various moves,
arithmetic/logical operations, jumps, call/return, SIMD extensions and
others. External functions are supported by allowing a user to provide
custom semantics for these calls. Floating-point operations are mapped
to uninterpreted functions. The model provides semantics for register
aliasing and a byte-level little-endian memory model. The semantics
are purposefully incomplete, but overapproximative. For example, the
precise effect of flags may be undefined for certain instructions, or
instructions may simply have no semantics at all. In those cases, the
semantics are mapped to universally quantified uninterpreted terms
from a locale. Second, this entry provides a method to symbolic
execution of basic blocks. The method, called
&#39;&#39;se_step&#39;&#39; (for: symbolic execution step) fetches
an instruction and updates the current symbolic state while keeping
track of assumptions made over the memory model. A key component is a
set of theorems that prove how reads from memory resolve after writes
have occurred. Thirdly, this entry provides a parser that allows the
user to copy-paste the output of the standard disassembly tool objdump
into Isabelle/HOL. A couple small and explanatory examples are
included, including functions from the word count program. Several
examples can be supplied upon request (they are not included due to
the running time of verification): functions from the floating-point
modulo function from FDLIBM, the GLIBC strlen function and the
CoreUtils SHA256 implementation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Algebras for Iteration, Infinite Executions and Correctness of Sequential Computations</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Correctness_Algebras.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Correctness_Algebras.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Walter Guttmann       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We study models of state-based non-deterministic sequential
computations and describe them using algebras. We propose algebras
that describe iteration for strict and non-strict computations. They
unify computation models which differ in the fixpoints used to
represent iteration. We propose algebras that describe the infinite
executions of a computation. They lead to a unified approximation
order and results that connect fixpoints in the approximation and
refinement orders. This unifies the semantics of recursion for a range
of computation models. We propose algebras that describe preconditions
and the effect of while-programs under postconditions. They unify
correctness statements in two dimensions: one statement applies in
various computation models to various correctness claims.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Verified Quadratic Virtual Substitution for Real Arithmetic</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Virtual_Substitution.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Virtual_Substitution.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Matias Scharager, Katherine Cordwell, Stefan Mitsch, André Platzer       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>02 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This paper presents a formally verified quantifier elimination (QE)
algorithm for first-order real arithmetic by linear and quadratic
virtual substitution (VS) in Isabelle/HOL. The Tarski-Seidenberg
theorem established that the first-order logic of real arithmetic is
decidable by QE. However, in practice, QE algorithms are highly
complicated and often combine multiple methods for performance. VS is
a practically successful method for QE that targets formulas with
low-degree polynomials. To our knowledge, this is the first work to
formalize VS for quadratic real arithmetic including inequalities. The
proofs necessitate various contributions to the existing multivariate
polynomial libraries in Isabelle/HOL. Our framework is modularized and
easily expandable (to facilitate integrating future optimizations),
and could serve as a basis for developing practical general-purpose QE
algorithms. Further, as our formalization is designed with
practicality in mind, we export our development to SML and test the
resulting code on 378 benchmarks from the literature, comparing to
Redlog, Z3, Wolfram Engine, and SMT-RAT. This identified
inconsistencies in some tools, underscoring the significance of a
verified approach for the intricacies of real arithmetic.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Soundness and Completeness of an Axiomatic System for First-Order Logic</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/FOL_Axiomatic.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/FOL_Axiomatic.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Asta Halkjær From       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>24 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This work is a formalization of the soundness and completeness of an
axiomatic system for first-order logic. The proof system is based on
System Q1 by Smullyan and the completeness proof follows his textbook
&#34;First-Order Logic&#34; (Springer-Verlag 1968). The completeness
proof is in the Henkin style where a consistent set is extended to a
maximal consistent set using Lindenbaum&#39;s construction and Henkin
witnesses are added during the construction to ensure saturation as
well. The resulting set is a Hintikka set which, by the model
existence theorem, is satisfiable in the Herbrand universe.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Complex Bounded Operators</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Complex_Bounded_Operators.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Complex_Bounded_Operators.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Jose Manuel Rodriguez Caballero, Dominique Unruh       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>18 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We present a formalization of bounded operators on complex vector
spaces.  Our formalization contains material on complex vector spaces
(normed spaces, Banach spaces, Hilbert spaces) that complements and
goes beyond the developments of real vectors spaces in the
Isabelle/HOL standard library.  We define the type of bounded
operators between complex vector spaces
(&lt;em&gt;cblinfun&lt;/em&gt;) and develop the theory of unitaries,
projectors, extension of bounded linear functions (BLT theorem),
adjoints, Loewner order, closed subspaces and more.  For the
finite-dimensional case, we provide code generation support by
identifying finite-dimensional operators with matrices as formalized
in the &lt;a href=&#34;Jordan_Normal_Form.html&#34;&gt;Jordan_Normal_Form&lt;/a&gt; AFP entry.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>A Formalization of Weighted Path Orders and Recursive Path Orders</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Weighted_Path_Order.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Weighted_Path_Order.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Christian Sternagel, René Thiemann, Akihisa Yamada       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>16 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
We define the weighted path order (WPO) and formalize several
properties such as strong normalization, the subterm property, and
closure properties under substitutions and contexts. Our definition of
WPO extends the original definition by also permitting multiset
comparisons of arguments instead of just lexicographic extensions.
Therefore, our WPO not only subsumes lexicographic path orders (LPO),
but also recursive path orders (RPO). We formally prove these
subsumptions and therefore all of the mentioned properties of WPO are
automatically transferable to LPO and RPO as well. Such a
transformation is not required for Knuth&amp;ndash;Bendix orders
(KBO), since they have already been formalized. Nevertheless, we still
provide a proof that WPO subsumes KBO and thereby underline the
generality of WPO.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Extension of Types-To-Sets</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Types_To_Sets_Extension.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Types_To_Sets_Extension.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mihails Milehins       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In their article titled &lt;i&gt;From Types to Sets by Local Type
Definitions in Higher-Order Logic&lt;/i&gt; and published in the
proceedings of the conference &lt;i&gt;Interactive Theorem
Proving&lt;/i&gt; in 2016, Ondřej Kunčar and Andrei Popescu propose an
extension of the logic Isabelle/HOL and an associated algorithm for
the relativization of the &lt;i&gt;type-based theorems&lt;/i&gt; to
more flexible &lt;i&gt;set-based theorems&lt;/i&gt;, collectively
referred to as &lt;i&gt;Types-To-Sets&lt;/i&gt;. One of the aims of
their work was to open an opportunity for the development of a
software tool for applied relativization in the implementation of the
logic Isabelle/HOL of the proof assistant Isabelle. In this article,
we provide a prototype of a software framework for the interactive
automated relativization of theorems in Isabelle/HOL, developed as an
extension of the proof language Isabelle/Isar. The software framework
incorporates the implementation of the proposed extension of the
logic, and builds upon some of the ideas for further work expressed in
the original article on Types-To-Sets by Ondřej Kunčar and Andrei
Popescu and the subsequent article &lt;i&gt;Smooth Manifolds and Types
to Sets for Linear Algebra in Isabelle/HOL&lt;/i&gt; that was written
by Fabian Immler and Bohua Zhan and published in the proceedings of
the &lt;i&gt;International Conference on Certified Programs and
Proofs&lt;/i&gt; in 2019.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>IDE: Introduction, Destruction, Elimination</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Intro_Dest_Elim.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Intro_Dest_Elim.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mihails Milehins       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
The article provides the command &lt;b&gt;mk_ide&lt;/b&gt; for the
object logic Isabelle/HOL of the formal proof assistant Isabelle. The
command &lt;b&gt;mk_ide&lt;/b&gt; enables the automated synthesis of
the introduction, destruction and elimination rules from arbitrary
definitions of constant predicates stated in Isabelle/HOL.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Conditional Transfer Rule</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Conditional_Transfer_Rule.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Conditional_Transfer_Rule.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mihails Milehins       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This article provides a collection of experimental utilities for
unoverloading of definitions and synthesis of conditional transfer
rules for the object logic Isabelle/HOL of the formal proof assistant
Isabelle written in Isabelle/ML.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Conditional Simplification</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Conditional_Simplification.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Conditional_Simplification.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mihails Milehins       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
The article provides a collection of experimental general-purpose
proof methods for the object logic Isabelle/HOL of the formal proof
assistant Isabelle. The methods in the collection offer functionality
that is similar to certain aspects of the functionality provided by
the standard proof methods of Isabelle that combine classical
reasoning and rewriting, such as the method &lt;i&gt;auto&lt;/i&gt;,
but use a different approach for rewriting. More specifically, these
methods allow for the side conditions of the rewrite rules to be
solved via intro-resolution.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Category Theory for ZFC in HOL III: Universal Constructions</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/CZH_Universal_Constructions.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/CZH_Universal_Constructions.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mihails Milehins       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
The article provides a formalization of elements of the theory of
universal constructions for 1-categories (such as limits, adjoints and
Kan extensions) in the object logic ZFC in HOL of the formal proof
assistant Isabelle. The article builds upon the foundations
established in the AFP entry &lt;i&gt;Category Theory for ZFC in HOL
II: Elementary Theory of 1-Categories&lt;/i&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Category Theory for ZFC in HOL I: Foundations: Design Patterns, Set Theory, Digraphs, Semicategories</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/CZH_Foundations.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/CZH_Foundations.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mihails Milehins       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This article provides a foundational framework for the formalization
of category theory in the object logic ZFC in HOL of the formal proof
assistant Isabelle. More specifically, this article provides a
formalization of canonical set-theoretic constructions internalized in
the type &lt;i&gt;V&lt;/i&gt; associated with the ZFC in HOL,
establishes a design pattern for the formalization of mathematical
structures using sequences and locales, and showcases the developed
infrastructure by providing formalizations of the elementary theories
of digraphs and semicategories. The methodology chosen for the
formalization of the theories of digraphs and semicategories (and
categories in future articles) rests on the ideas that were originally
expressed in the article &lt;i&gt;Set-Theoretical Foundations of
Category Theory&lt;/i&gt; written by Solomon Feferman and Georg
Kreisel. Thus, in the context of this work, each of the aforementioned
mathematical structures is represented as a term of the type
&lt;i&gt;V&lt;/i&gt; embedded into a stage of the von Neumann
hierarchy.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Category Theory for ZFC in HOL II: Elementary Theory of 1-Categories</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/CZH_Elementary_Categories.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/CZH_Elementary_Categories.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Mihails Milehins       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This article provides a formalization of the foundations of the theory
of 1-categories in the object logic ZFC in HOL of the formal proof
assistant Isabelle. The article builds upon the foundations that were
established in the AFP entry &lt;i&gt;Category Theory for ZFC in HOL
I: Foundations: Design Patterns, Set Theory, Digraphs,
Semicategories&lt;/i&gt;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>A data flow analysis algorithm for computing dominators</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Dominance_CHK.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Dominance_CHK.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Nan Jiang       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>05 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This entry formalises the fast iterative algorithm for computing dominators
due to Cooper, Harvey and Kennedy. It gives a specification of computing
dominators on a control
flow graph where each node refers to its reverse post order number. A
semilattice of reversed-ordered list which represents dominators is
built and a Kildall-style algorithm on the semilattice is defined for
computing dominators. Finally the soundness and completeness of the
algorithm are proved w.r.t. the specification.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Solving Cubic and Quartic Equations</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Cubic_Quartic_Equations.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Cubic_Quartic_Equations.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> René Thiemann       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>03 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
&lt;p&gt;We formalize Cardano&#39;s formula to solve a cubic equation
$$ax^3 + bx^2 + cx + d = 0,$$ as well as Ferrari&#39;s formula to
solve a quartic equation. We further turn both formulas into
executable algorithms based on the algebraic number implementation in
the AFP. To this end we also slightly extended this library, namely by
making the minimal polynomial of an algebraic number executable, and
by defining and implementing $n$-th roots of complex
numbers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Logging-independent Message Anonymity in the Relational Method</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Logging_Independent_Anonymity.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Logging_Independent_Anonymity.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Pasquale Noce       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>26 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
In the context of formal cryptographic protocol verification,
logging-independent message anonymity is the property for a given
message to remain anonymous despite the attacker&#39;s capability of
mapping messages of that sort to agents based on some intrinsic
feature of such messages, rather than by logging the messages
exchanged by legitimate agents as with logging-dependent message
anonymity.
This paper illustrates how logging-independent message
anonymity can be formalized according to the relational method for
formal protocol verification by considering a real-world protocol,
namely the Restricted Identification one by the BSI. This sample model
is used to verify that the pseudonymous identifiers output by user
identification tokens remain anonymous under the expected conditions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>The Theorem of Three Circles</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Three_Circles.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Three_Circles.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Fox Thomson, Wenda Li       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
The Descartes test based on Bernstein coefficients and Descartes’ rule
of signs effectively (over-)approximates the number of real roots of a
univariate polynomial over an interval. In this entry we formalise the
theorem of three circles, which gives sufficient conditions for when
the Descartes test returns 0 or 1. This is the first step for
efficient root isolation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Fresh identifiers</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Fresh_Identifiers.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Fresh_Identifiers.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Andrei Popescu, Thomas Bauereiss       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
This entry defines a type class with an operator returning a fresh
identifier, given a set of already used identifiers and a preferred
identifier.  The entry provides a default instantiation for any
infinite type, as well as executable instantiations for natural
numbers and strings.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
       <title>Combinatorial Design Theory</title>
              <link>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Design_Theory.html</link>
       <guid>https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Design_Theory.html</guid>
       <dc:creator> Chelsea Edmonds, Lawrence Paulson       </dc:creator>
       <pubDate>13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
       <description>
Combinatorial design theory studies incidence set systems with certain
balance and symmetry properties. It is closely related to hypergraph
theory. This formalisation presents a general library for formal
reasoning on incidence set systems, designs and their applications,
including formal definitions and proofs for many key properties,
operations, and theorems on the construction and existence of designs.
Notably, this includes formalising t-designs, balanced incomplete
block designs (BIBD), group divisible designs (GDD), pairwise balanced
designs (PBD), design isomorphisms, and the relationship between
graphs and designs. A locale-centric approach has been used to manage
the relationships between the many different types of designs.
Theorems of particular interest include the necessary conditions for
existence of a BIBD, Wilson&#39;s construction on GDDs, and
Bose&#39;s inequality on resolvable designs. Parts of this
formalisation are explored in the paper &#34;A Modular First
Formalisation of Combinatorial Design Theory&#34;, presented at CICM 2021.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
